<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Random Walks</title>
        <link>https://ykumar.org/</link>
        <description><![CDATA[posts and musings]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://ykumar.org//rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Lord of the Flies</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//lord-of-the-flies</link>
    <description><![CDATA[kids and pigs]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//lord-of-the-flies</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Toledo</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//toledo</link>
    <description><![CDATA[2AM Amtrak layovers]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//toledo</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Geneva</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//geneva</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on September 11, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Geneva is evil.</p>
<p>It’s overpriced, loud, and dirty. Paying ten francs for a medicore street taco is no way to live life. God forbid you visit the city center during the day, and stay as far away from Geneva station as you can. I thought the air was supposed to be good in the Alps?</p>
<p>But above all, it <em>reeks</em> of <em>fakeness.</em></p>
<p>It calls itself the “Peace Capital”, claims it’s too good to have twin cities, and prides itself on its cosmopolitanism. On what grounds? Before Hitler’s fall, Geneva’s only claim to facilitating international diplomacy was hosting the League of Nations – admittedly the best international governing body we’ve had thus far, but still. After, every international organization and their shadow backers clamored to have their headquarters (or at least their European headquarters) in Geneva. The UN, WHO, UNHCR, Red Cross, WTO, WIPO, WMO, ILO, …</p>
<p>Did you know that the largest non-financial services industry in Geneva is <em>watchmaking?</em> Rolex, Patek Philippe, etc. have factories just outside of Geneva proper. To be fair, ‘financial services’ also excludes commodity trading, of which Geneva is to oil, sugar, grains, and coffee as Rotterdam is to metals. Vitol &amp; Trafigura both have their headquarters in Geneva (and one must wonder whether or not this is for convenience or to take advantage of lax Swiss banking laws…remember Marc Rich?)</p>
<p>Two-thirds of the corporate tax in Geneva comes from commodity trading, banking, and watchmaking. These international organizations? Don’t contribute to the economy. (Yes, they bring people &amp; these people use services &amp; this allows Geneva natives to benefit from the overwhelming amount of NGOs and international bodies in their city. Still.)</p>
<p>Tragically, Geneva once had a soul. The ‘Protestant Rome’ which once served as the birthplace of the Calvinist Revolution was annexed by Catholic France &amp; revolted as a response. The city had <em>opinions</em> that informed its <em>identity</em> – not a pseudo-identity formed from undeserved arrogance &amp; globalism.</p>
<p>Demographic shifts (mostly French immigration to French-speaking Switzerland) led to Catholics forming the largest religious group in Geneva today, followed by atheists. (I am not blaming immigration for Geneva’s soullessness! it is just another piece of the puzzle). This, along with its absurd emphasis on being a truly international city, undergird the sense that <em>Geneve</em> has lost its way.</p>
<p>And the Jet d’Eau… really? Geneva really had to take the self-masturbatory imagery to another level…</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//geneva</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Slaughterhouse-Five</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//slaughterhouse-five</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 26, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <h2 id="rating-25">Rating: <strong>2/5</strong></h2>
<p>Vonnegut, at least this incarnation, bores me. It shouldn’t – Slaughterhouse-Five draws on his own experience, his own lived experience, and that at minimum should draw me in – but the humor falls flat, the characterizations seem shallow, and it reads as a puzzle for the reader to solve rather than a proper story. Certainly an interesting enigma, however .</p>
<h2 id="humor">Humor</h2>
<p>Irony is a recurring theme in satirical anti-war books (it is the entire premise of Catch-22 after all). The case of Edgar Derby is no exception, and it is one of the highlights in my opinion. Although, I can’t stop wondering how a <em>teapot</em> survived the Dresden bombings. Maybe this is the irony, that the teapot survived while he didn’t.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I think the climax of the book will be the execution of poor old Edgar Derby,” I said. “The irony is so great. A whole city gets burned down, and thousands and thousands of people are killed. And then this one American foot soldier is arrested in the ruins for taking a teapot. And he’s given a regular trial, and then he’s shot by a firing squad.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We can’t forget the origination of the most popular Tralfamadorian phrase of all time:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Early in 1968, a group of optometrists, with Billy among them, chartered an airplane to fly them from Ilium to an international convention of optometrists in Montreal. The plane crashed on top of Sugarbush Mountain, in Vermont. Everybody was killed but Billy. So it goes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>While Billy was recuperating in a hospital in Vermont, his wife died accidentally of carbon-monoxide poisoning. So it goes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It gets tiring after some time, however. The incessant reminder of the dichotomy between Tralfamadorian death and human death serves to trivialize it, not highlight it.</p>
<p>There’s some cool foreshadowing with the concept of “baby-ness”:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>And we were flown to a rest camp in France, where we were fed chocolate malted milkshakes and other rich foods until we were all covered with baby fat. Then we were sent home, and I married a pretty girl who was covered with baby fat, too.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Soldiers turn from men to babies after the war; they become civilized, softer from the perspective of Billy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>So then I understood. It was war that made her so angry. She didn’t want her babies or anybody else’s babies killed in wars…
“I tell you what,” I said, “I’ll call it ‘The Children’s Crusade.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But from the onlooker’s perspective, babies go to war and become men.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The American fliers turned in their uniforms, became high school kids. And Hitler turned into a baby, Billy Pilgrim supposed. That wasn’t in the movie. Billy was extrapolating. Everybody turned into a baby, and all humanity, without exception, conspired biologically to produce two perfect people named Adam and Eve, he supposed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And from the Tralfamadorian perspective, they just watch it in reverse sometimes. Its a good euphemistic mechanism for Vonnegut to describe the horrors of war from different perspectives. The soldiers view it as a a regression to a more primal state, their families view it as them growing up too fast too quickly, and the omniscient onlooker simply doesn’t care.</p>
<h2 id="tralfamadorian-takes">Tralfamadorian Takes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I hadn’t spent so much time studying Earthlings,” said the Tralfamadorian, “I wouldn’t have any idea what was meant by ‘free will.’ I’ve visited thirty-one inhabited planets in the universe, and I have studied reports on one hundred more. Only on Earth is there any talk of free will.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t think that it’s possible for Tralfamadorians to exist (but we leave the metaphysical arguments for another day).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>On Tralfamadore, says Billy Pilgrim, there isn’t much interest in Jesus Christ. The Earthling figure who is most engaging to the Tralfamadorian mind, he says, is Charles Darwin—who taught that those who die are meant to die, that corpses are improvements. So it goes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This, this is funny. The natural extension of survival of the fittest &amp; natural selction to a truly timeless perspective, where birth and death are irrelevant to the existence of a being, is simply that death is a strictly superior state to being alive. Hilarious.</p>
<p>If you assume the Tralfamadorians are a metaphor for Billy’s coping mechanism, or a plot device to showcase the horrors of war from a satirical lens, then the novel reads much more clearly as anti-war, and you can examine Billy’s mental state as one would study a character in a Dostoevsky novel.</p>
<p>Yet, their repetitive, blatant timeless nature being constantly thrown in your face, with no regard to how such a species could in fact survive (let alone be the default!) simply undermines this effort. At least make it realistic! such that there’s ambiguity in interpretation. If something is blatantly intended to be a metaphor it loses its power.</p>
<h2 id="a-product-of-its-time">A Product of its Time?</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Billy Pilgrim says now that this really is the way he is going to die, too. As a time-traveler, he has seen his own death many times, has described it to a tape recorder. The tape is locked up with his will and some other valuables in his safe-deposit box at the Ilium Merchants National Bank and Trust, he says.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>I, Billy Pilgrim, the tape begins, will die, have died, and always will die on February thirteenth, 1976.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At the time of his death, he says, he is in Chicago to address a large crowd on the subject of flying saucers and the true nature of time. His home is still in Ilium. He has had to cross three international boundaries in order to reach Chicago. The United States of America has been Balkanized, has been divided into twenty petty nations so that it will never again be a threat to world peace. Chicago has been hydrogen-bombed by angry Chinamen. So it goes. It is all brand new.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Billy is speaking before a capacity audience in a baseball park, which is covered by a geodesic dome. The flag of the country is behind him. It is a Hereford bull on a field of green. Billy predicts his own death within an hour. He laughs about it, invites the crowd to laugh with him. “It is high time I was dead,” he says. “Many years ago,” he said, “a certain man promised to have me killed. He is an old man now, living not far from here. He has read all the publicity associated with my appearance in your fair city. He is insane. Tonight he will keep his promise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Kudos to Vonnegut for getting the geodesic dome right (featured in the Chicago World Fair). But the Balkanization of the US? Nuclear war, yet not armageddon, caused by the Chinese? This is an interesting insight into the ideology of the 1960s anti-war left (we will antagonize China by engaging heavily in Southeast Asia, therefore this seems likely), or perhaps this is meant to be inherently implausible to further highlight the irony of it all.</p>
<p>(I do note, this book was published in the same year that we went to the moon. Counterculture fascination with aliens at the time?)</p>
<p>Then there’s Montana Wildhack.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Billy mentioned casually that he had seen part of a blue movie she had made. Her response was no less casual. It was Tralfamadorian and guilt-free:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Yes—” she said, “and I’ve heard about you in the war, about what a clown you were. And I’ve heard about the high-school teacher who was shot. He made a blue movie with a firing squad.” She moved the baby from one breast to the other, because the moment was so structured that she had to do so.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Billy’s ultimate escapist fantasy: going to an alien planet with a loving, hot, girl to bang whenever time gets hard. A fantasy shared by men of all ages, in all times, that came to the fore in the Sexual Revolution and still remains true to this day.</p>
<p>So it goes.</p>
<p><em>Also on <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5550704561">Goodreads</a>.</em></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//slaughterhouse-five</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Silence of the Lambs</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//the-silence-of-the-lambs</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 16, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <h2 id="rating-25">Rating: <strong>2/5</strong></h2>
<p>I began to read this book expecting a decent representation of insanity, and I finished it because it was a half-decent thriller.</p>
<p>The misogyny runs deep: nearly every interaction Starling has with her male compatriots is tinged with either sexual undertones, patronizing, or unearned arrogance. Ironically, the two who treat her the best are Lecter and Crawford, and Lecter isn’t exactly the paragon of morality.</p>
<p>It is interesting that Buffalo Bill is described as someone who desires to be a ‘transsexual’ yet isn’t. This book would never have been written today, as a doctor denying someone their gender identity seems to be anathema in modern culture. Yet, the author goes to great pains to separate the criminality of the killer from the supposed criminality of transgender individuals through the mouth of the doctors at JHU. Moreover, this book’s relationship to sexuality is quite strange.</p>
<p>Crawford is shown as a shadow of his former self (his implied former self, I haven’t read the first book). Bella dies near the climax, and as a result he is recused from Buffalo Bill’s final arrest. He barely has any interaction with Lecter, which is a shame (the two would have great chemistry, as I suspect they do in the rest of the series). Starling’s obsession with Crawford is framed as some combination of a crush and desire for a father-figure, which gets somewhat culled by the end.</p>
<p>I expected Lecter to be the best part of the novel, and he certainly was. A deus ex machina in the flesh that has just enough of a veneer of justification to be considered a character. If you ignore his “intelligent feats”, his relationship with Starling is truly absurd.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Clarice, recreational flayings are always conducted with the victim inverted, so that blood pressure is maintained longer in the head and chest and the subject remains conscious. Didn’t you know that?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“No.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps the best embodiment of the trope of the “rational psychopath”: certainly entertaining, but not that interesting (not like Raskolnikov).</p>
<p>May read the rest in the series. Not necessarily high quality, but one of the better thrillers.</p>
<p><em>Also on <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5468502558">Goodreads</a>.</em></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//the-silence-of-the-lambs</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Invisible China</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//invisible-china</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 15, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <h2 id="rating-35">Rating: <strong>3/5</strong></h2>
<p>Pretty good. Made me think, and Rozelle’s unique perspective (economist who’s spent 30+ years on the ground) adds an authentic flavor to the book.</p>
<p>He claims that the existential threat to China’s potential future growth and success is a lack of human capital: specifically, that systemic factors hinder rural Chinese children’s ability to participate effectively in the service-based, advanced economy of the 21st century, and that fixing this issue is imperative so that China does not fall into the middle income trap.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a 2004 article in Foreign Affairs, political scientist Geoffrey Garrett shared a startling observation. He looked at the history of recent economic development and noticed that while rich countries were continuing to do well and many poor countries were achieving strong growth rates, the countries in the middle of the global income spectrum were growing more slowly and less successfully than anyone else.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In a report that made ripples throughout the development world, economists at the World Bank demonstrated the full extent of the problem. The report showed that out of 101 countries that were middle income in 1960, only thirteen had made it to high-income status by 2008. The rest remained stuck or even ended the fifty years poorer than before.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The middle income trap is the stagnation developing countries face when their average citizen reaches a “middle income.” An easy way for developing countries to rapidly grow their economies is to accept industrialization and foreign direct investment, shifting to a manufacturing economy reminiscent of Western nations in the 1890s. However, Rozelle makes the argument that to then shift from a middle income to high income country requires an educated populace, and the middle-income countries which have failed to continue their economic growth did not appropriately invest in the education of their citizenry.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But with a bit of historical data, another trend emerges that is far more relevant to the question at hand: the very small number of countries that have made it out of middle-income status in recent decades—the graduates—all have very high levels of high school education. Even more surprising, they’ve had those high levels for decades. In particular, back when they were still middle income, the graduates (places like South Korea, Taiwan, and Ireland) all had high school attainment rates comparable to those of the rich countries.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>China is not appropriately investing in the necessary amounts of education to avoid the middle income trap. While they may have the necessary innovation, all the Baidus, Tencents, and Bytedances in the world wouldn’t fix the systemic issue of having nearly 70% of its population without a high school education unable to participate in the high-skilled, high-paid industries that characterize high-income countries.</p>
<p>Rural Chinese mainly work low-skilled manufacturing jobs, or jobs which don’t require a high school education. This was fine, until rising wages in mainland China started pushing manufacturing jobs overseas, leaving hundreds of thousands, if not millions of workers unemployed. Throughout the book, Rozelle includes telling anecdotes of workers who lost their job and couldn’t get a new one because they didn’t have the required skillset.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>…We fell into conversation with one man in particular. Mr. Wang was about thirty-five and had recently been laid off from his job of eighteen years as an electrician.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As we watched, Mr. Wang gamely sidled up to the first booth, which represented a bank. The man running the booth, a human resources staff member, shook his hand and asked him to read a short page of text and comment on what he understood. Mr. Wang stared hard at the piece of paper, trying to force the characters into an order he could understand. He knew all the words and could read them aloud, but many of the terms were over his head. He kept getting confused by the logic of the sentences. For several minutes he stared at it, trying to make sense of what he was seeing. At first the man running the booth was patient and seemed sympathetic, but gradually the bank representative lost interest, turned back to his desk, and started looking around for workers who might be a better bet. After a few more minutes, Mr. Wang lowered his head with a sigh: “I’m sorry, I just can’t make sense of it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As it turns out, simply increasing access and/or mandating a high school education wouldn’t be enough. The rural/urban divide in China runs deep. The opportunity &amp; outcome differential comes not only from unequal access to education and other outgrowths of the <em>hukou</em> policy, but also from deep-seated systemic differences. ‘Vocational’ schooling is a joke:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Tao’s middle school teacher suggested he check out the new vocational high school that had recently opened across town… When he arrived on campus a week later, he found himself in an unfamiliar world. Whereas his middle school had been orderly and regimented, here chaos reigned. The older students were tough-looking, with tight jeans, black pleather jackets, and spiked hair. As he walked to class on his first day, there were no adults in sight. He passed groups of kids hanging out in the courtyard, smoking cigarettes and laughing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Children who grow up in rural China suffer from three “invisible epidemics”, as Rozelle calls them: anemia, uncorrected myopia, and parasitic intestinal worms. Iron-deficiency anemia has been linked to dramatic decreases in IQ, myopia (for obvious reasons) impedes learning ability, and worms almost literally sap the life force from their hosts. Luckily, cheap and safe interventions can fix these issues. Iron supplements, subsidized glasses, and cheap, common medicine could easily bring the health of a Chinese kid in the country to within striking distance of one in Beijing.</p>
<p>Perhaps a harder problem to fix is that of crucial stimulation of children during their formative developmental years. Rural parenting strategies are unequipped to give a child sufficient intellectual stimulation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In rural China, babies are systematically missing out on the mental stimulation they need. When we asked rural families if they ever talked to their babies, we were met with blank looks or bemused smiles. “Why would I talk to my baby?” one young mother responded, giggling into her hand. “She can’t talk back!”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yet, this leads to delayed infant development, and the permanent stunting of a child’s ability relative to their peers. Rural chinese babies score horribly on the Bayley test, while urban Chinese children score higher than average. This seems to be much of the issue.</p>
<p>For the sake of China and the world, Rozelle hopes that China will be able to fix its human capital crisis. He is somewhat bullish: the Chinese government is beginning to recognize that this is an issue, and some sane policies have been implemented. But he wants more to be done. Maybe China can pull off an economic miracle again, but this seems to be a major roadblock.</p>
<p><em>Also on <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/edit/51941583">Goodreads</a>.</em></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//invisible-china</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Crime and Punishment</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//crime-and-punishment</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 11, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <h2 id="rating-55">Rating: <strong>5/5</strong></h2>
<p>A masterpiece.</p>
<p>Briefly: the plot is passable, the writing (admittedly translated) is at times laborious to read. But Raskolnikov’s many foils never fail to disappoint.</p>
<p>Dostoevsky’s genius was to take ‘soul-shattering’ events literally. The murderer’s soul was, in fact, split apart, and each one of his shards has a coherent storyline – his failings as a brother are reflected in his relationship with Razumikhin, his descent into insanity is paralleled by the poor case of Katerina Ivanova, and his inner Napoleon finally manages to submit itself in the face of God.</p>
<p>Razumikhin is, if not the best, the most wholesome character in the novel. He is loyal where Raskolnikov is not, forgiving where Raskolnikov is not, and loving where Raskolnikov is not. Ultimately, he usurps his erstwhile friend as both brother and son, and it is perhaps no wonder he had a happy ending.</p>
<p>Katerina Ivanova, Sonia’s mother, goes mad in the penultimate part of the novel. Her madness was of natural origins, caused by ‘an Act of God’, and involuntary – while Raskolnikov’s was anthropogenic, brought unto himself by himself, and voluntary (he knew!).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Yes, and you maintained that the perpetration of a crime is always accompanied by illness.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The contrast could not be starker. His illness was psychosomatic, hers was tuberculosis. His insanity was prolonged, hers was brief. His psychosis concealed the truth from others, hers hid the truth from herself. Raskolnikov’s suffering was <em>synthetic</em>, plastic, shallow – the antithesis of her organic pain.</p>
<p>It is wrong to consider Raskolnikov a socialist, almost as wrong as considering him a Christian. Instead, he is an egoist in the truest sense of the word:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I simply hinted that an ‘extraordinary’ man has the right . . . that is not an official right, but an inner right to decide in his own conscience to overstep . . . certain obstacles, and only in case it is essential for the practical fulfillment of his idea (sometimes, perhaps, of benefit to the whole of humanity). You say that my article isn’t definite; I am ready to make it as clear as I can. Perhaps I am right in thinking you want me to; very well. I maintain that if the discoveries of Kepler and Newton could not have been made known except by sacrificing the lives of one, a dozen, a hundred, or more people, Newton would have had the right, would in fact have been duty bound . . . to eliminate a dozen or a hundred men for the sake of making his discoveries known to the whole of humanity.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Socialist desires equality of outcome and therefore criminality is the responsibility of Society; the Christian respects the dignity of the self, so criminality is the responsibility of the individual; and Raskolnikov says that Society should just suck it up when great people do bad things insofar as they’re contributing to the aesthetic advancement of Society.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In short, I maintain that all great people or even people who are slightly uncommon, that is to say capable of producing some new idea, must by nature be criminals—more or less, of course. Otherwise it’s hard for them to get out of the common rut; and to remain in the common rut is what they can’t submit to, from their very nature again, and to my mind they ought not, in fact, to submit to it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Napoleon killed hundreds of thousands, if not millions! Why is he not decried as a scourge upon humanity while a petty philanderer is sentenced to the eighth circle of Hell? Because he was Great of course, and all Great men must become a criminal in service of their Greatness.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“What if it were really that?” he said, as though reaching a conclusion. “Yes, that’s what it was! I wanted to become a Napoleon, that is why I killed her . . . Do you understand now?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Except he wasn’t.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Don’t interrupt me, Sonia. I want to prove one thing only, that the devil led me on then and he has shown me since that I did not have the right to take that path, because I am just a louse like all the rest.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Crime and Punishment is a story of salvation, and each one of Raskolnikov’s parts must be saved. As a brother and son, he could have been saved by repenting to his family (he could have been Razumikhin). As a a maniac, perhaps he could have found peace in nihilism, as a proleteriat, perhaps he would have found solidarity with his fellow common man. But as an egoist, he perceives himself above the rest, and Dostoevsky claims his only repentance is submission to the Almighty.</p>
<p>This is but a fraction of what makes this work great, and it’s been analyzed to death by high schoolers and Harvard professors alike. Still an amazing read.</p>
<p><em>Also on [Goodreads].</em></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//crime-and-punishment</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Hyperreals in a Nutshell</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//hyperreals-in-a-nutshell</link>
    <description><![CDATA[The number system which begets nonstandard analysis (and nonstandard Peano arithmetic, but that's for another day)]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//hyperreals-in-a-nutshell</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Three Body Problem</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//the-three-body-problem</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on April 22, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <h2 id="rating-35">Rating: <strong>3/5</strong></h2>
<p>I have a weakness for marginally-better-than-average sci-fi, and this is definitely better than most sci-fi books I’ve read. (Which may be a sad reflection on the state of decent scifi worldbuilding).</p>
<p>Great fun to read! despite the difficulty of translation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“You also taught the big bang theory. This is the most reactionary of all scientific theories.” One of the male Red Guards spoke up, trying to change the subject.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Maybe in the future this theory will be disproven. But two great cosmological discoveries of this century—Hubble’s law, and observation of the cosmic microwave background–show that the big bang theory is currently the most plausible explanation for the origin of the universe.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Lies!” Shao Lin shouted. Then she began a long lecture about the big bang theory, remembering to splice in insightful critiques of the theory’s extremely reactionary nature. But the freshness of the theory attracted the most intelligent of the four girls, who couldn’t help but ask, “Time began with the singularity? So what was there before the singularity?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Nothing,” Ye said, the way he would answer a question from any curious young person. He turned to look at the girl kindly. With his injuries and the tall iron hat, the motion was very difficult.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“No … nothing? That’s reactionary! Completely reactionary!” the frightened girl shouted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The descriptions of the Cultural Revolution were vivid, horrific, and historically plausible. I am boggled that I had not understood the depth to which Maoist China was trapped in a ideological fervor.</p>
<p>Anti-intellectual movements were common in Communist regimes (from the USSR to Mao to Pol Pot) as well as in fascist ones (Hitler attempted to exterminate Polish intellectuals), but it never occured to me that a <em>populist, leftist student movement</em> would denounce empiricism in the name of an ideology. And this forms the basis of Ye Wenjie’s belief in the irredemable nature of humanity.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was impossible to expect a moral awakening from humankind itself, just like it was impossible to expect humans to lift off the earth by pulling up on their own hair. To achieve moral awakening required a force outside the human race.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Humanity is Evil crops up in The Three-Body Problem quite a bit - is the justification for Frontiers of Science and calling for the Trisolarian incursion. This book was written in 2006, perhaps before the heyday of the climate movement? but it is interesting how self-loathing on a macro-level can lead to such horrific actions. Ye Wenjie <em>became what she strove to destroy</em> when she killed her husband and superior at the altar of her cause, but nevertheless stopped short of calling for humanity’s extinction (Mike Evans did that for her).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Someone truly neutral will then be able to comment on whether we’re the heroes or villains of history. [from the Central Leadership of the CCP]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Quite funny that the CCP is described here as unsure of their standing in history. Perhaps another example of the leaders of movements having less zealotry than their followers.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most people did not want to be indispensable, because they understood that in highly classified projects like this, once someone was put into a core technical position, it would be very difficult for him to be transferred out. Thus, all of them tried to deliberately hide their technical competence as they went about their jobs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The description of Red Coast was telling: simultaneously high-status yet inefficient by dint of its nature as a classified endeavor. Ecosystems like this manifest whenever incentive structures are sufficiently misaligned (I should probably specify this claim more, but words fail me at the moment). System alignment is hard and aligning the goals of agents in a system with the system’s goals is a hard problem.</p>
<h2 id="characters">Characters</h2>
<p>Da Shi is an interesting character. He’s the perfect foil to the <em>intelligensia</em> who populate the main cast, but he’s too perfect? From the moment you meet him you can instantly predict that he will be “the street-smart person who saves the protagonist’s hide”, and the trope usage is just the cherry on top (rebellious, but the C/O lets him stick around? really?)</p>
<p>The transition from:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Shi’s questions irritated Wang again, not unlike the feeling a man has upon finding out that he has swallowed a fly with his meal.
to in the final moments of the book:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I bet you’re happy to be proven right. There really was someone behind all this.” Wang forced himself to smile, hoping Da Shi could see it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>is predictable yet half-satisfying.</p>
<p>Wei Cheng is described as this otherworldly mathematical prodigy who does math instinctively, and as a result never has to work hard at it. Despite his genius, he’s lackadaisical, and is unmotivated until he encounters the three body problem, at which point he becomes obsessed with finding order in the chaos. This characterization is decently interesting, especially when put into context of his relationship with Shen Yufei, but I have a hard time believing that he would get nerdsniped by the <em>three-body problem</em> of all things?</p>
<p>I didn’t find Wang Miao particularly interesting as a main character. Ye Wenjie works very well, but her total confession at the end makes less sense than I would have wanted it to. Mike Evans is too farcical to take seriously. The rest don’t really register as interesting to me.</p>
<h2 id="trisolaris">Trisolaris</h2>
<p>Using the Three-Body Problem as the underpinnings of the book was a good idea! Even if from a mathematics perspective the problem is quite simple, the symbolism of simplicity breeding chaos is too good to pass up.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans took more than a hundred thousand Earth years to progress from the Hunter-Gatherer Age to the Agricultural Age. To get from the Agricultural Age to the Industrial Age took a few thousand Earth years. But to go from the Industrial Age to the Atomic Age took only two hundred Earth years. Thereafter, in only a few Earth decades, they entered the Information Age. This civilization possesses the terrifying ability to accelerate their progress.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“On Trisolaris, of the more than two hundred civilizations, including our own, none has ever experienced such accelerating development. The progress of science and technology in all Trisolaran civilizations has been at a constant or decelerating pace. In our world, each technology age requires approximately the same amount of time for steady, slow development.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Linear progress vs. exponential progress is an interesting demarcation between humans and Trisolarians, and this leads to the development of the sophon. I <em>loved</em> the descriptions of the sophon-failures, especially the three dimensional one.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>People noticed the eyes moved faster than the other solids filling the sky, and they were gathering into one spot. Soon, two eyes met and merged into one bigger eye. More and more eyes joined this big eye, and its volume grew. Finally, all the eyes melded into one. It was so large that it seemed to represent the gaze of the universe upon Trisolaris. The iris was clear and bright, and at the center was the image of a sun. Over the broad surface of the eyeball, various colors cascaded in a flood. Soon, the details over the giant eye faded and gradually disappeared, until it became a pupil-less blind eye. Then it began to deform until it finally lost the shape of an eye and became a perfect circle. When the circle began to slowly rotate, people realized that it was not flat, but parabolic, like a slice cut from a giant sphere.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Creeeeepy.</em></p>
<p>Hidden dimensions are an underutilized resource in the sci-fi I’ve read, and very stoked to see them represented here!</p>
<p><em>Also on <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5461651116">Goodreads</a>.</em></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//the-three-body-problem</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>five ways to say "Almost Always" and actually mean it</title>
    <link>https://ykumar.org//almost-always</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on April 19, 2023
        
            by Yudhister Kumar
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <h2 id="in-english">In English</h2>
<p>A boring, colloquial way.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all the eggs are gone!” (as half a dozen remain)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="not-finite-ness">Not-Finite-ness</h2>
<p>A slightly-less-boring mathy way.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all prime numbers are odd!</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are infinitely many primes. There is exactly one even prime number (2). Infinity minus one is… infinity.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all natural numbers are larger than one-hundred thousand quadrillion quadrillion vigintillion! (10^83)</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are infinitely many natural numbers. There are infinitely many natural numbers larger than one-hundred thousand quadrillion quadrillion vigintillion. No practical difference between 10^83 and 1 (other than that one is an upper bound on the number of atoms in the universe).</p>
<p>You formalize this with sets: if you have some (infinite) set, a subset whose complement has a finite cardinality encompasses almost everything in the set. We call this <em>cofiniteness.</em></p>
<h2 id="probability-one">Probability ~One</h2>
<p>A way to quantify surety.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all the people will lose money at the casino!</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m not sure what the exact rates are, but I’d bet money on this being true.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all numbers are composite!</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is well known that the number of prime numbers below <span class="math inline"><em>N</em></span> is approximately <span class="math inline"><em>N</em>/ln <em>N</em></span>. In the limit as \(N\) goes to infinity, the ratio of primes to non-primes numbers goes to approximately zero. So if you choose a random positive integer, I would bet my life savings that it’s composite.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all graphs are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org//wiki/Asymmetric_graph">asymmetric</a>.</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An intuitive explanation: if you take all possible combinations of nodes and vertices and let the number of each tend towards infinity, you should expect chaos to triumph over order. (sorry Ramsey). This does depend on a certain definition of symmetry, however, and a clearer statement would be “<em>almost all graphs have only one automorphism.</em>”</p>
<h2 id="the-lebesgue-measure-is-not-zero">The Lebesgue Measure is Not-Zero</h2>
<p>A straightforward-yet-strange way for real numbers.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebesgue_measure">Lebesgue measure</a> is what you get when you try to generalize length, area, and volume to \(n\)-dimensions. It forms the basis for our current understanding of integration, and helps us figure out how big stuff is.</p>
<p>Something with zero volume basically doesn’t exist anyway.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all real numbers are irrational!</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well yes, all the rationals have measure zero. All countable sets have measure zero, and the rationals are countable.</p>
<p>(Measures are nice: they’re a neat generalization of physical scales (mass, volume, etc.) to arbitrary mathematical objects. They’re particularly useful for dealing with continuous things <del>we love Lebesgue measures</del>)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all real numbers are noncomputable!</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well yes? Of course an arbitrary real number can’t be computed to arbitrary precision by a finite algorithm? <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computable_number">Computable numbers</a> are <em>countable,</em> remember? Nevermind that <em>basically all the numbers we deal with are computable,</em> this is <em>obvious.</em></p>
<p>(Measure zero stuff basically doesn’t exist, even if they’re the only things we use on a daily basis)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all real numbers aren’t in the Cantor set!</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well yes, of course! Even though the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cantor_set">Cantor set</a> is uncountably infinite, it still has measure zero! It’s a weird pseudo-fractal embedding of the real line that somehow manages to lose everything in translation but still keep all the relevant information.</p>
<p>(Idk, the Cantor set is weird)</p>
<h2 id="it-is-contained-in-a-nonprincipal-ultrafilter">It is Contained in a Nonprincipal Ultrafilter</h2>
<p>A <em>filter</em> <span class="math inline">ℱ</span> on an arbitrary set \(I\) is a collection of subsets of \(I\) that is closed under set intersections and supersets. (Note that this means that the smallest filter on \(I\) is \(I\) itself).</p>
<p>An <em>ultrafilter</em> is a filter which, for every <span class="math inline"><em>A</em> ⊆ <em>I</em></span>, contains either \(A\) or its complement. A <em>principal</em> ultrafilter contains a finite set.</p>
<p>A <em>nonprincipal ultrafilter</em> does not.</p>
<p>This turns out to be an incredibly powerful mathematical tool, and can be used to generalize the concept of “almost all” to esoteric mathematical objects that might not have well-defined or intuitive properties.</p>
<p>(One of the coolest uses of nonprincipal ultrafilters is in the construction of the hyperreals, post forthcoming).</p>
<p>Let \(\) be a nonprincipal ultrafilter over the natural numbers. It obviously contains no finite sets, but we run into a slight issue when we take the set
\[
E = \{2,4,6,8, \ldots \}
\]
and its complement
\[
O = \{1,3,5,7, \ldots \}.
\]
By the filter axioms, only one of these can be in \(\), and one of them <em>has</em> to be in \(\). And thus, we can safely say:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“<em>Almost all natural numbers are <strong>even</strong>.</em>”</p>
</blockquote>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://ykumar.org//almost-always</guid>
    <dc:creator>Yudhister Kumar</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
